Guide to the Delmore Schwartz Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Delmore Schwartz papers
1906-1975
1926-1966
YCAL MSS 334
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
23.3
(29 boxes)
The Delmore Schwartz Papers document the life and work of the writer, editor, and teacher Delmore Schwartz. The papers consist of writings, notebooks, correspondence, photographs, personal papers and effects, drawings, clippings, and printed material. Writings and notebooks comprise the bulk of the papers. Writings include drafts of poems, stories, essays, reviews, criticism, lectures, and other writings. Notebooks span two decades and document Schwartz's increasingly troubled mind and frantic writings, containing a hybrid of writing drafts and personal diary entries. The papers also include correspondence with friends and colleagues, revealing his intimate but often troubled friendships, professional relationships, and two marriages. Personal and professional papers of Schwartz contain records of his divorce from Elizabeth Pollet, teaching files and financial materials, drawings, collected clippings, and other papers. The papers also contain photographs of Schwartz, his family and friends, and literary events. The papers span the years 1906-1975.
Schwartz, Delmore, 1913-1966
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Kenneth Schwartz on the E.J. Beinecke Fund, 1975 and 1981; and from Lame Duck Books on the Carl Van Vechten Fund, 2002. Gift of James Atlas, 1981 and Dwight McDonald, 1982.
Custodial History
The Delmore Schwartz Papers contains material of mixed provenance. In 1962, Schwartz left Manhattan to live in Syracuse, New York and abandoned his belongings. An individual hired to move the materials recognized Schwartz's name and stored them for several years until he transferred them to Dwight Macdonald, who was executor of Schwartz's estate. Upon Schwartz's death in 1966 in Manhattan, Macdonald retrieved the remaining papers from his last hotel room. Materials left behind in Syracuse were discovered in 1976 and transferred to the George Arents Research Library. In 1981, these materials were sent to the Beinecke Library to comprise the Delmore Schwartz Papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 29: Restricted fragile material. A digital reference surrogate is available in Beinecke Digital Collections. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm service copies are available.
Separated Materials
Printed material received with the collection was removed for separate cataloging and can be accessed by searching the library's online catalog.
Delmore Schwartz
Delmore Schwartz was born in Brooklyn, New York on December 8, 1913 to Romanian-born immigrants Harry and Rose Schwartz. His only sibling, Kenneth, was born in 1916. Harry Schwartz was a successful real estate businessman and Delmore Schwartz grew up comfortably middle class. In 1923, his parents separated and in 1927 they officially divorced. Their tumultuous marriage would be the source of anger and disappointment for Schwartz in his writings and future relationships. Schwartz developed an erratic relationship with his Jewish heritage that remained throughout his life, vacillating between engaged optimism and resentment of his parents' generation's traditional ways. Harry Schwartz lost most of his money in the 1929 market crash and died in 1930. The family received none of the little inheritance left after the estate executor embezzled the remaining funds. The crime never went to trial and Rose Schwartz was left to be the sole provider for Delmore and Kenneth.
Schwartz displayed an early talent for reading and writing but struggled in the rest of his studies. While in high school, he published a few poems in the high school literary magazine and was encouraged by teachers to study English in college. After graduation from George Washington High School, Schwartz enrolled in a college prep course at Columbia University and in 1931 he transferred to the University of Wisconsin. He thrived there, being exposed to avant-garde literature and art. Although he was a curious student, his grades were poor and he returned to New York City in 1932. He enrolled at New York University and studied with philosopher, Marxist scholar, and student of John Dewey, Sidney Hook. Hook's influence was profound on Schwartz's studies and early ideas of becoming a writer. Schwartz co-founded and edited the literary magazine Mosaic, in which he published his own essays and caught the attention of other New York writers. He moved to Greenwich Village in his junior year, began writing a purported twelve hours a day, and it was there that he began to make the acquaintance of the New York literary community. He graduated with a B.A. in philosophy in 1935. In July of the same year, Schwartz wrote his short story "In Dreams Begin Responsibilities." That fall he started graduate studies in philosophy at Harvard but never finished his degree. Through 1936, he wrote prolifically, published poems in Poetry and American Caravanmagazine, and won the Bowdoin Prize in the Humanities for his essay, "Poetry as Imitation." In the spring of 1937, Schwartz ran out of funds and returned to New York, beginning his work full time as a writer and critic.
"In Dreams Begin Responsibilities" appeared in the 1937 debut issue of Partisan Review, the left-wing magazine started by Philip Rahv and William Phillips. Schwartz's story appeared alongside writings by famous and influential figures, such as Sidney Hook and Edmund Wilson. His story and its success pushed him into the spotlight and he quickly became a writer to watch, with critics comparing him to W.H. Auden and Hart Crane. A year later, New Directions published Schwartz's first collection of poems and stories, In Dreams Begin Responsibilities. It received immediate and intense praise by many, including Ezra Pound, T.S Eliot, William Carlos Williams, Robert Lowell, and Vladimir Nabokov. In 1938, Schwartz married Gertrude Buckman, a fellow NYU graduate. The marriage was unhappy from the beginning and ended in divorce six years later.
Successfully published, Schwartz began his teaching career. He was hired as a lecturer and then Assistant Professor at Harvard University. He taught at several institutions throughout his life, including Bennington College, Kenyon College, Princeton University, and finally at Syracuse University. Many other schools extended invitations. Students admired him and he maintained a strong influence on his students. Schwartz also received several fellowships and grants throughout his life, including a Guggenheim Fellowship, the Shelley Memorial Prize, a Fulbright fellowship (he canceled it amidst his second divorce), a grant by the National Institute of Arts and Letters, and a residency at the writer's colony Yaddo. In 1940, Schwartz addressed the Modern Language Association, delivering his "The Isolation of Modern Poetry." Genesis: Book I, a semi-autobiographical piece, intended as the first installment of a multi-volume epic, was published in 1943 and received unfavorable criticism. Schwartz began to doubt his writing abilities.
During his late twenties, Schwartz's alcoholism, drug abuse (he favored barbiturates and amphetamines), and acute depression developed and began to affect his marriage, friendships, and ability to work. Easily angered and increasingly paranoid, he created emotional distances in most of his relationships and struggled to maintain professional contacts with other writers. Other writers respected Schwartz's talent and work but found it difficult to weather his accusations of artistic jealousy, plagiarism, and gossip. Despite his interpersonal challenges, he maintained the role of an important writer and literary figure. He alienated most of his friends but a few remained devoted to him, refusing to relent to his accusations and delusions, including Dwight Macdonald, Saul Bellow, John Berryman, and William Barrett.
In 1948, after leaving Harvard suddenly in 1947, Schwartz published a book of short stories, The World is a Wedding. Critics and literary figures praised it but it failed to sell many copies. His work was widely anthologized during this time and he was considered by some to be the most anthologized poet of his generation. He published critical essays on important literary figures, film and television, and was poetry editor at Partisan Review and later at The New Republic.
Schwartz married Elizabeth Pollet, a younger writer and former student at Black Mountain College, in 1949. The couple moved from New York to rural northern New Jersey to concentrate on their writing. Schwartz became increasingly unwell, drinking even more, and succumbing to paranoid delusions. Pollet left Schwartz in the fall of 1955, after enduring years of his erratic and abusive behavior, and stayed with a friend in a location she kept secret from Schwartz. Schwartz reacted with violent anger and his most elaborate paranoid delusion to date. He moved back to New York and checked into the Chelsea Hotel; accused Pollet of having an affair with art critic and editor of Arts magazine, Hilton Kramer (who barely knew Pollet); physically attacked Kramer in his apartment after repeatedly calling him on the telephone; and was consequently arrested in his hotel room and brought to Bellevue Hospital. After a stay in Bellevue, he was transferred to Payne-Whitney Clinic. Once released from the clinic, Schwartz began to file complaints and lawsuits. One affidavit accused Kramer, Pollet, James Laughlin, Marshall Best, Saul Bellow, The Living Theatre, William Styron, Perry Miller, and Harry Levin of conspiracy against him. Others were subpoenaed. Schwartz eventually narrowed his attack to just Kramer and the legal affair dragged on for years.
Schwartz was often unwell, but he sometimes maintained periods of calm. In 1958, he gave the lecture, "The Present State of Modern Poetry," at the Library of Congress and was interviewed by Randall Jarrell. In 1960 he was awarded the Bollingen Prize for poetry, making him the youngest poet to receive the prestigious prize. After The World is a Wedding, none of his other published works received the same praise as his earlier work. He wrote little that interested others in the last six years of his life and most of his writing activity was filling up notebooks and leaves of paper with lengthy and often illegible writings.
Schwartz's final teaching post was at Syracuse University. Although his appearance was unkempt and he was a severe alcoholic, he had a robust student following. Musician Lou Reed was among his students and Schwartz had a great influence on Reed as a poet and musician. Reed dedicated the instrumental song "European Sun" on the Velvet Underground's first album to Schwartz (according to Reed, Schwartz didn't like song lyrics). Schwartz left Syracuse in January 1966 to return to Greenwich Village, where he resumed drinking at the White Horse Tavern, a favorite of his for years. He was often seen alone in parks or the New York Pubic Library, writing in notebooks.
Schwartz died at the age of fifty-three of a heart attack on July 11, 1966 in a hallway of the Columbia Hotel in Greenwich Village. His body went unclaimed at the morgue for two days until friends were alerted to his death. In the years after his death, there was a resurgence of interest in his work. John Berryman, Saul Bellow, and Robert Lowell are among the writers that profess Schwartz's influence on their own work. Lowell considered him to be the most underrated poet of the century. Bellow's 1973 novel Humboldt's Gift, which won the Pulitzer Prize, is a semi-fictional memoir about Schwartz.
Other published works by Schwartz include Shenandoah (1941), Vaudeville for a Princess and Other Poems (1950), Summer Knowledge: Selected Poems (1938-1958) (1959), and Successful Love and Other Stories (1961).
Scope and Contents
The Delmore Schwartz Papers document the life and work of the writer, editor, and teacher Delmore Schwartz. The papers consist of writings, notebooks, correspondence, professional and personal papers, photographs, drawings, clippings, personal effects, and printed material spanning the years 1906-1975, with the bulk of the material dating from the period 1926-1966.
The papers primarily document Schwartz's life as a writer, including drafts of poems, stories, essays, reviews, criticism, lectures, other writings, and writings of others. His erratic creative process is revealed through the drafts of writings: at times he was focused, working on holograph and typescript drafts of poems and stories methodically, and other times he filled pages with nearly illegible handwriting and overlapping sentence fragments. Among the writings of others is Schwartz's copy of James Joyce's Finnegan's Wake, of which every page contains his dense annotations. Schwartz's notebooks span two decades and document his increasingly troubled mind and frantic writings, containing a hybrid of writing drafts and personal diary entries.
The papers also include correspondence with friends and colleagues, revealing his intimate but often troubled friendships, professional relationships, and two marriages. Professional and personal papers of Schwartz relate to his divorces from Gertrude Buckman and Elizabeth Pollet, his lawsuit against Hilton Kramer, and his teaching and finances, and include drawings, clippings, and other papers. Clippings and other printed material contains published writings on Schwartz, but the bulk of it is articles of interest to Schwartz. The papers also contain photographs of Schwartz, his family and friends, and literary events.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1937-1966. II. Writings, 1926-1966. III. Notebooks, 1939-1966. IV. Personal and Professional Papers, 1936-1966. V. Photographs, 1906-circa 1975.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; American drama -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographs; Authors; Editors; Macdonald, Dwight, 1906-1982; Pollet, Elizabeth, 1922-; Schwartz, Delmore, 1913-1966; New Directions Publishing Corp
- Correspondence, 1937-1966, undated; Series I; 1.42; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is arranged into two subseries: General Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
  The correspondence series contains correspondence between Schwartz and friends and colleagues. Letters are incoming unless otherwise noted. Correspondence relates to Schwartz's writings, finances, personal life, and work as a teacher. Much of the correspondence regards contractual agreements, his financial instability, and writings of others. Some letters regard interpersonal strife among friends and acquaintances. Despite the amount of correspondence, little of it discusses the main events, works, and friendships of Schwartz's life.
  A 1965 letter from Lou Reed discusses Reed's consideration of graduate school, his desire to be a poet and his new music career, and his affection and respect for Schwartz. Letters from Victoria Bay regard the difficulties her relationship with Schwartz, a letter from Ted Berrigan accompanies a copy of his The Sonnets, and letters from James Laughlin relate to the friendship between the two and publishing agreements between Schwartz and New Directions.
  Among the correspondents are many notable writers, such as W. H. Auden, William Barrett, John Berryman, T.S. Eliot, Randall Jarrell, Robert Lowell, Julian Beck of Living Theatre, Marcia Nardi, Philip Rahv, Stephen Spender, and Allen Tate.
  - General Correspondence
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Letters by those identified by first names only, outgoing letters to people not listed, unidentified and financial correspondence, delivery confirmations, and empty envelopes are filed at the end of the series.
    - "A" general, 1955-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Atlantic Monthly, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Art News, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "B" general, 1939-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Barrett, William, 1942-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Basler, __, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bay, Victoria, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bellow, Saul, 1956 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Berrigan, Ted, circa 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes Berrigan's The Sonnets
    - Berryman, John, 1946-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Blackmur, Helen, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Blackmur, Richard, 1941-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Boudreau, Eugene, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bousquet, Alain, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Broyard, Anatole, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Brown, Edward, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Buckman, Gertrude, 1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "C" general, 1942-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Carpenter, Margaret, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Clark, Anthony, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Commentary, 1947-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Cooper, Pat, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Covici, Pascal, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "D" general, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Dike, Donald, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Doubleday and Company, inc., 1958-1965 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "E" general, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Eliot, T. S., 1939-1953 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Elliott, George P., 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Esquire, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Evett, Robert, 1952-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "F" general, 1957-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Farrar, Straus and Giroux, Inc., 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Fitts, Dudley, 1943 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Fitelson and Mayers, 1957 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Flint, Robert, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Ford Foundation, 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Foreign Service of the United States of America, 1957 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Fulbright Commission, 1957 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - "G" general, 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Garrigue, Jean, 1943-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Goff, Eleanor, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Gruenthal, Lola, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Gruenthal, Max, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - "H" general, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Halio, Jay, 1962 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Includes Halio's writing, "Delmore Schwartz's Felt Abstractions"
    - Handlin, Oscar, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Harrisson, Gilbert A., 1954-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Hartle, Pat, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Harvard University, 1939-1956 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Henry, Kenneth, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Herschberger, Ruth, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Howe, Irving, 1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Hutchins, Robert, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - "I" general, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Jarrell, Randall, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1940, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - "K" general, 1943-1965 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Kaplan, J. M., 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Katz, __, 1945, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Krim, Sy, 1959 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - "L" general, 1946-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Laughlin, James, 1940-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Lewis, Richard, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Library of Congress, 1957-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Living Theatre, 1959 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Lowell, Robert, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Lynes, Carlos, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Lytle, Andrew, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - "M" general, 1943-1966 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Macdonald, Dwight, 1937-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Mackin, Cornelia W., 1949, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Macleish, Archibald, 1955 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Marshall, Margaret, 1957 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Maxwell, William, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Morrison, Theodore, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Moss, Howard, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - "N" general, 1953-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Nardi, Marcia, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - The Nation, 1952 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - New Directions Publishing Corp., 1939-1964 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - The New Republic, 1955-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - The New Yorker, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - "O" general, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Odell, __, 1964 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - "P" general, 1955-1965 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Palmer, John, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Partisan Review, 1958-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Perspectives, 1952 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Phillips, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Poetry, 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Pollet, Elizabeth, 1944-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Princeton University, 1943-1953 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - "R" general, 1953-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Rahv, Philip, 1943-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Ransom, John C., 1952-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Reed, Lou, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - The Reporter, 1955 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 100)
    - Russell, __, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - "S" general, 1943-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 102)
    - S & O Associates, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 103)
    - Scarlett, Emily, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 104)
    - Schapiro, Meyer, 1939-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - Schwartz, Harry, 1943-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - Schwartz, Kenneth, 1948 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 107)
    - Schwartz, Rose, 1944 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 108)
      Outgoing letter
    - Shapiro, Karl, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 109)
    - Slavitt, David, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 110)
    - Smith, Bill, 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 111)
    - Spender, Stephen, 1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 112)
    - Syracuse University, 1958-1966 (Box 1, Folder 113)
    - "T" general, 1957-1965 (Box 1, Folder 114)
    - Tate, Allen, 1939, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 115)
    - Tolley, William Pearson, undated (Box 1, Folder 116)
    - Trilling, Lionel, 1954 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 117)
    - "U" general, 1954-1965 (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - United States. Dept. of State, 1957 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 119)
    - United States Information Agency, 1956 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 120)
    - "V" general, 1955-1980 (Box 1, Folder 121)
    - "W" general, 1951-1965 (Box 1, Folder 122)
    - Who's Who in America, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 123)
    - Williams, Oscar, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 124)
    - Wilson, Angus, 1956 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 125)
    - Wolf, Leonard, 1957 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 126)
    - Yaddo (Artist's colony), 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 127)
    - Yale University, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 128)
    - Zabel, Morton Dauwen, 1950 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 129)
    - Zolotow, Maurice, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 130)
    - __, Arthur, 1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - __, Holmes, undated (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - __, Klip, 1946 April 9 (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - __, Mark, 1941-1946 (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1943-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 135)
      Letters to people not listed above
    - Unidentified correspondence, 1943-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 136)
    - Financial correspondence, 1943-1959 (Box 2, Folder 137)
    - Delivery confirmations, 1963-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 138)
    - Empty letter envelopes, 1941-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 139-140)
  - Third Party Correspondence
    - To William Barrett from David Way, 1947 August 1 (Box 2, Folder 141)
      Regards Elizabeth Pollet